Guide to the Carole De Saram Papers 1972-2011 MS 3059
New-York Historical Society
Carole De Saram papers
1972-2011
New-York Historical Society
De Saram, Carole
MS 3059
11.5 Linear feet in 11 record cartons, 1 document box, and 1 over-size folder
The Carole De Saram papers include materials gathered and produced by De Saram as a result of her involvement in Tribeca community affairs. De Saram is both the former Chair of Community Board 1 in Manhattan and the former President of the Tribeca Community Association. The bulk of the content is textual with some photographs, maps, and ephemera included.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in two series: Subject Files and Publications. The Subject Files comprise 10 record cartons and 1 over-size folder and the Publications, 1 record carton.
Biographical / Historical
Carole De Saram is both the former Chair of Community Board 1 (CB#1) in Manhattan and the former President of the Tribeca Community Association (TCA). Active in the Tribeca community for over 40 years, De Saram witnessed and shaped the development of this historical area. She was also influential in the feminist movement and is the former president of the New York City chapter of the National Women's Organization (NOW). An interview with Carole De Saram was conducted by The New York Preservation Archive Project, which can be found here.
In the 1970s, many artists moved into Tribeca's large and inexpensive lofts, creating a progressive community in a mostly industrial section of Manhattan and stimulating desirability. Around this time, the name Tribeca was coined for the "Triangle below Canal" Street, previously known as Washington Square Market. De Saram became involved with CB#1 and the TCA and helped organize the process of designating Tribeca as a landmark historic district in the 1980s. The area was split into four separate landmark districts: Tribeca North, East, South and West. De Saram felt strongly about issues that affected quality of life for Tribeca residents. These ranged from environmental concerns, noise and light pollution, open space initiatives, and safety considerations. Development in Tribeca saw a tremendous boom starting in the 1980s. De Saram paid careful attention to zoning laws and changes, strategizing legal action when CB#1 and the TCA felt building preservation and community well-being were threatened by developers.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift from Carole De Saram, 2016, with some additional photographs received in 2018.
Related Materials
Oliver Allen papers on the historic preservation of Tribeca, MS 3058.
Scope and Contents
The materials in the Carole De Saram papers generally relate to development and quality of life issues, landmark designations, community supported projects, and lawsuits that affected Tribeca.
Series I includes correspondence, press releases, memorandum, minutes, articles, resolutions, newsletters, meeting notices, booklets, handbooks, brochures, pamphlets, journals, photographs, ephemera, maps, guides, and legal documents that were gathered and produced by De Saram as a result of her involvement in Tribeca community affairs. Many specific buildings, addresses, developers, and corporations are documented within these papers. New York City government departments including the Board of Standards and Appeals, the Landmarks Preservation Commission, the City Planning Commission, and the Department of Sanitation are also represented. More detailed information pertaining to topics, names, and places covered by each subheading can be found in the collection inventory scope and contents notes.
Series II consists of publications such as booklets, guides, pamphlets, brochures, ephemera, periodicals, manuals and reports.
TriBeCa (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; TriBeCa (New York, N.Y.); Tribeca East Historic District (New York, N.Y.); Tribeca North Historic District (New York, N.Y.); Tribeca South Historic District (New York, N.Y.); Tribeca West Historic District (New York, N.Y.); Actions and defenses -- New York (State) -- New York.; City planning -- New York (State) -- New York.; Community organization.; Historic buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Historic districts -- New York (State) -- New York.; Historic preservation -- New York (State) -- New York.; Parks -- New York (State) -- New York.; Public health -- New York (State) -- New York.; Skyscrapers.; Women in community organization.; Zoning law.; Allen, Oliver E.; Bromm, Hal; De Saram, Carole; Dolkart, Andrew; Gayle, Margot; Committee for the Washington Market Historic District; Community Board 1 (Manhattan, New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.). Landmarks Preservation Commission; Tribeca Community Association
- Series 1: Subject Files, 1972-2011; 10 Linear feet and 1 over-size folder
  Scope and Contents
  Series I includes correspondence, press releases, memorandum, minutes, articles, resolutions, newsletters, meeting notices, booklets, handbooks, brochures, pamphlets, journals, photographs, ephemera, maps, guides, and legal documents that were gathered and produced by De Saram as a result of her involvement in Tribeca community affairs. Many specific buildings, addresses, developers, and corporations are documented within these papers. New York City government departments including the Board of Standards and Appeals, the Landmarks Preservation Commission, the City Planning Commission, and the Department of Sanitation are also represented. More detailed information pertaining to topics, names, and places covered by each subheading can be found in the collection inventory scope and contents notes.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged following an inventory list produced by De Saram that accompanied the collection. The topical subject headings listed on this document, reflecting her organizational schema, were retained for the Subject File subheadings. These subheadings are:
  Landmarks Designation Research and Issues
  TCA / NYC Zoning Changes and Battles
  416-424 Washington Street
  Tribeca Community Association Developer and Zoning Lawsuits
  Shearson - American Express - City Planning Council Rezoning of Washington Market
  Lower Manhattan Tribeca Reports and Plans
  Traffic Studies, Sanitation Garage & Salt Facility, and Realize Hudson Rise Alternative Plan
  Hudson River and Route 9A Development
  Tribeca Community Association Quality of Life Issues – Lawsuits
  Tribeca Parks Founded by Community
  Texture of Tribeca Book
  Tribeca Community Association (TCA) Papers
  The files within each Series I subheading have been arranged by roughly descending bulk order, so that the files with the most material appear first within each subheading. The materials were received in labeled folders, often with notes about the contents written on the folder. These original notes are transcribed within the file's scope and contents note when they supplied information supplementary to the title. The folders are not archival, but have been retained since they are annotated by the creator. The original folders along with their contents were rehoused in archival folders as a precautionary measure against acid migration. As another preservation measure, the newsprint in each folder has been enclosed within archival paper slings to prevent it from damaging surrounding papers.
  At the close of the series is a set of photographs received separately from the main body of the documents.
  - Landmarks Designation Research and Issues: (Box -, Folder -)
  - Landmarks Designation, 1984-2008 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-8)
  - LPC Buildings Department Forms, 1984-1986 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9-12)
    Original folder reads: "Landmark Survey Forms - Data obtained from Municipal Archive files for Landmark Commission to designate Tribeca an historic district. Some data was from architect filings since there was no data available or required before 1890."
  - LPC Research Forms, 1985-1986 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    Original folder reads: "Research forms for LPC designator report. City of NY did not have records for buildings before 1869. Only records available were architectural reports. Found in the City archives in dead storage, They may not be available anymore."
  - Landmark Building Permits, 1989-2001 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
  - LPC Tribeca Buildings Index, 1985 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
    Printout on fan-fold paper that includes building block, lot, style and architect. Listed in ascending geocode order.
  - LPC Tribeca Buildings Index, 1985 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
    Printouts and photocopies of fan-fold paper that includes building block, lot, style and architect. Listed in ascending block and lot order.
  - Landmark Support Letters, 1986-2002 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
  - Tribeca West Historic District Designation Report, 1991 May (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  - Archaeological Historical Sensitivity Analysis Report, 1987-1988 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  - Tribeca North Historic Designation Report, 1992 December (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  - Tribeca South Historic District Designation Report, 1992 December (Offsite-box 2, Volume 1)
  - Tribeca East Historic District Designation Report, 1992 December (Offsite-box 2, Volume 2)
  - John Street / Maiden Lane Historic District, 1986-2003 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - Sugar Warehouse (1 of 2 folders), 2000 January 12 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
    Handwritten note on first page of document reads: "Sugar warehouse used for Confederate soldiers. Chains were placed in the walls. Some still remain."
  - Sugar Warehouse (2 of 2 folders) over-size, 2000 January 12 (Box over-size small)
    The Sugar Warehouse 79 Laight Street, New York NY. Site Plan and Zoning Analysis. Packet of architectural drawings and renderings.
  - Tribeca African American History, 1991-2006 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
    Contains handwritten notes, ephemera from the Wesley Chapel Museum, and single articles related to the African Burial Ground historic designation by the LPC in 1993, Sojourner Truth, and Seneca Village.
  - Royal Bank of Canada, 1991 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
    Note on documents reads: "Royal Bank of Canada to construct an office building, 68-76 William Street".
  - LPC Public Hearings, 1986-1994 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - Prince of Wales, 1987-1988 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
    Original folder reads: "Copy of US speech on preservation. Sent to Tribeca Community Association".
  - Mathew Brady, 1991 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
    Original folder reads: "359 Broadway Studio. First photo of Abraham Lincoln. '359 Brady's Gallery' sign painted over in 1988. Petition signed by P.S.234 students to save building. They won."
  - Miscellaneous Landmark Pictures, 1983-1989 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
    Photocopies of historic drawings and modern photographs.
  - Anthony Tung, Landmark Commissioner, 1988-1990 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
    Original folder reads: "Anthony Tung, Landmark Commissioner 1979-1988. Not re-appointed by Mayor David Dinkins.
  - Margot Gayle, Cast Iron, 1978-1993 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - Badger Catalogue, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
    Original folder reads: "Badger Catalogue, Washington Market Survey building list. 1811-1935 building list."
  - TCA / NYC Zoning Changes and Battles (Box -, Folder -)
  - Commodity Exchange Case (1 of 3), 1992 July 24 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
    Copy of summons for the Supreme Court of the State of New York, County of New York case brought against the NYS Urban Development Corporation, the Commodity Exchange Inc. (COMEX) et al. by the Tribeca Community Association et al.
  - Commodity Exchange Case (2 of 3), 1992 (Offsite-box 2, Volume 3)
    Copy of Plantiffs' memorandum of law in opposition to motion to dismiss and in support of cross-motion for summary judgement.
  - Commodity Exchange Case (3 of 3), 1992 November 24 (Offsite-box 3, Volume 1)
    Notice of cross-motion and case exhibits A-W.
  - Board of Standards and Appeals / Ramirez Project, 2003-2004 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
    The Ramirez Project refers to a proposal from Samuel Ramirez Jr. to build a structure at 408 Greenwich Street that would both house his family's bond trading business and create residences. Some residences were designed for the Ramirez family and others were designated for rental units. Ramirez had to obtain a zoning variance approval from the BSA for the planned nine story structure because the lot was only zoned for six stories. Community Board # 1, the Tribeca Community Association, and many Tribeca neighbors opposed the height of this building, feeling it would block views from nearby residences and clash with the character of the neighborhood. They also took issue with how a hardship variance could be granted for the construction of four luxury condominiums, two of which would be for the personal use of the Ramirez family. In the end, Ramirez was granted variance approval from the BSA and the building designed by his hired architect, Morris Adjmi, was completed in 2008.
  - Board of Standards and Appeals / Ramirez Project, 2004-2005 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
    In 2004, the TCA et al. brought a case to the Supreme Court of the State of New York County of New York, against the NYC BSA and Ramirez Properties, LLC, to vacate, set aside, and annul the approval of the BSA zoning variance to Ramirez Properties which allowed the construction of a nine story structure at 408 Greenwich Street. This folder contains photocopies of case documents.
  - Rezoning Lower Broadway / Lower Manhattan Mixed-Use District, 1983-2004 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3-5)
    Original folders read: "Letters. Press. Commodity Exchange aka Drexel aka COMEX Plan".
  - Tribeca North Rezoning (2 of 3 folders), 2004-2006 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6-7)
    Original folders read: "Press. Letters: elected officials, CB#1, TCA et al. Truffles LLC aka Jack Parker aka Ponte Properties".
    Contains flyers and community signed petitions for the "Stop the Wall" campaign.
  - Tribeca North Rezoning (3 of 3 folders) over-size, undated (Box over-size small)
    Photograph of vehicles parked in a lot at the corner of Debrosses and Washington Street, looking north.
  - 105 Duane Street High Rise, 1988-1992 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
    Original folder reads: "Record Search City Hall. 4T to DOF and US Department of Justice."
    This folder documents CB#1 and the TCA's opposition to the 52 story building at 105 Duane Street between Church and Broadway during both the planning and implementation stages.
  - NYC Planning and Zoning, 1992 January 30 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
    Two booklets prepared by The New York City Department of City Planning titled, "Planning and Zoning New York City Yesterday Today and Tomorrow" and "A Brief Profile of Today's City and Trends for the Future, Addressing Demographics, the Economy, Land Use, Infrastructure, and Quality of Life." Accompanied by a program detailing the panel discussions and reception information.
  - 60 Warren Street and West Broadway, 1988-2000 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
    Original folder reads: "5 Stories atop a Landmark Building"
  - Chinatown Prison - Walker Street, 1982 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
  - Reade and Hudson Street site, 1987-1989 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
    Original folder reads: "115 unit building, 14 stories. Application denied after TCA contacted City Planning Commission." The LPC had approved the project, but the Department of Buildings denied the plan and the project was shut down.
  - Tribeca Grand Hotel, 1999 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
    Original folder reads: "Triangle, Sixth Avenue and White and Walker Streets"
  - 60 Hudson Street, 1996-2003 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
    Original folder reads: "former Western Union Building - fuel tank oil permit"
  - 48 Laight Street, 1999-2003 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
    Original folder reads: "Corner of Laight Street and Hudson Street".
  - Beach Street, 1983-2004 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
    Original folder reads: "Street eliminated from Greenwich to West Street for Shearson/AMEX".
  - 88 Laight Street, 2003-2006 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
    Original folder reads: "Building exceeded building height. Had to remove floors".
  - New York Law School, 2006-2011 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
    Original folder reads: "Leonard and Church Streets"
  - Tribeca Buildings Zoning Changes, 1983-2007 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - NYC Public Spaces, 2000 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
    Original folder reads: "NYC granted through PGM 316 public spaces. Some are not open to the public - see NYT's list".
  - 416-424 Washington Street (Box -, Folder -)
    De Saram's notes read: "Major zoning lawsuit against gun warehouse - 10 years - aka Imperato, aka Amore Holdings. Hotel 416-424 Washington Street. 256 West Street, American Savings Bank, Brewran West, Lori Albar. Congressman Nadler FDIC lawsuit. 2005 new project approved."
    Detailed information about the Nadler vs. FDIC lawsuit can be found here. The TCA was also listed as a plantiff in these lawsuits.
  - Washington Street Urban Renewal Area, 1984 May (Offsite-box 4, Volume 1)
    Sixth Amended Plan, Canal to Vesey, Final Environmental Impact Statement
  - Legal Records from Nadler vs. FDIC lawsuit, 1994-1997 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - Board of Standards and Appeals Public Hearing Transcript, 1999 February 24 (Offsite-box 4, Volume 2)
    Public Hearing Concerning the Application for a Variance for the Hudson Hotel and Conference Center in Tribeca, New York. Calendar number: 180-95-BZ
  - 416 Washington Street Warehouse Pile Logs, 2000 October 16 (Offsite-box 4, Volume 3)
  - Letters, Notices, Flyers, and Press, 1984-2003 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4-9)
  - Letters, Notices, and Flyers re: Board of Standards and Appeals, 1993-2000 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
  - Board of Standards and Appeals Hearings, 1996-2002 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
    Original folder reads: "Imperato Corp, Gun Warehouse, Brewran West, 32 Story 'Low-end Hotel', Boymelgreen - Residential"
  - Invoices related to Nadler vs. FDIC lawsuit, 1994-2002 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
  - Hotel Environmental Impact Statement (1 of 2 folders), 1999-2000 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
  - Hotel Environmental Impact Statement (2 of 2 folders) over-size, 2001 (Box over-size small)
    Hudson Center Residential Project architectural drawings (4 pages)
  - Expert Testimonies for Board of Standards and Appeals, 1983-2002 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
  - Nadler vs. FDIC lawsuit - Consultant Reports, 1984-2008 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
  - Board of Standards and Appeals Hearing Minutes, 1999 July 21 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
    Calendar number 180-95-BZ. Premises affected: 256 West Street and 416/24 Washington Street, Borough of Manhattan.
  - Public meeting before Landmarks Preservation Commission, 1994 September 20 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
    In the matter of 416-424 Washington Street, aka 57-65 Vestry Street, Tribeca North Historic District (unproofread transcript)
  - Hotel - Statement of Facts and Summary of Pending Violations, 1997-1998 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
  - Memorandum in opposition to hotel, 1999 February 11 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 8)
    Memorandum and Supporting List of Exhibits Opposing Application for Variance and Commenting Upon Draft Environmental Impact Statement. BSA Calendar Number: 180-95-BZ
  - Supplemental Draft Environmental Impact Statement for the Hudson Center Residential Project, 2000 June 15 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 9)
    BSA Calendar Number: 180-95-BZ CEQR Number 96-BSA-048M Prepared for the NYC Board of Standards and Appeals
  - Hotel / Hudson Center Tower Project, 1992-2000 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10)
  - Community Board #1 Resolutions, 1993-1999 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10)
  - Landmarks Preservation Commission, 1994 July 26 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 11)
    In the Matter of 414-424 Washington Street
  - Tribeca Community Association Developer and Zoning Lawsuits (Box -, Folder -)
  - Citi Bank Red Umbrella Travelers Logo - Letters, Notices, Flyers, and Press, 1991-1998 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 12)
    Documents removed from three ring binder titled, "Umbrella"
  - Citi Bank Red Umbrella Travelers Logo - Board of Standards and Appeals Hearing, 1997 November 18 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1)
    Calendar Number: 152-97-A
  - Citi Bank Red Umbrella Travelers Logo - Lawsuit and Press, 1996-2002 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 2)
  - 415 Washington Street - Building Project Proposal Documents, 2005-2006 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 3)
    Includes CB#1 resolutions images of site, Statement of Facts and Findings, Proposed F.A.R. Residential Layout, DOB Notice of Objections, Environmental Assessment Statement and Supplemental Report, Economic Analysis, and Evaluation of Subsurface and Environmental Conditions
  - 415 Washington Street - Letters, Notices, Press, and Plans (1 of 2 folders), 1999-2006 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
    Includes a transcript of the Board of Stands and Appeals hearing on October 31, 2006. Case #: 128-06-BZ
  - 415 Washington Street - Letters, Notices, Press, and Plans (2 of 2 folders) over-size, 2006 (Box over-size small)
    Architectural drawings by Fairchild & Foster Atelier (11 pages)
  - Shearson - American Express - City Planning Council Rezoning of Washington Market (Box -, Folder -)
    De Saram's notes read: "Lawsuit by Council member Ruth Messinger, State Senator Frans Leichter, Congressman Ted Weiss and TCA. Beach Street eliminated for Shearson/AMEX building."
    These documents relate to the 1984 Article 78 petition filing in State Supreme Court by the Tribeca Community Association et al. asking that the Board of Estimate decision approving a Sixth Amended Plan to the Washington Street Urban Renewal Area and permitting construction of a downtown office tower by Shearson Lehman/American Express, be vacated.
  - Lawsuit - Legal records, Memorandum, and Letters, 1983-1984 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5)
  - Calendar of the Board of Estimate, 1984 June 28 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 6)
    Includes zoning changes to the Lower Manhattan Mixed Use District highlighted by De Saram.
  - Zoning (1 of 2 folders), 1983-1995 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7)
    Includes correspondence between the TCA and other parties regarding the Shearson / American Express building development, legal fees, rezoning in Tribeca, and P.S. 234.
  - Zoning (2 of 2 folders) over-size, 1983-1995 (Box over-size small)
    Two aerial photos of Tribeca with yellow arrows depicting "subject" and "site" respectively. One copy of the Washington Market Review (November 21, 1984) with an article about The Shearson Deal.
  - Rezoning - Letters, Notices, Flyers and Press, 1983-1987 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 8-9)
    Also includes petitions signed by Tribeca residents
  - Court Documents, 1984 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 10-11)
    Includes annotated case documents and a draft of the lease and land disposition agreement between NYC and Shearson Lehman/American Express Inc.
  - Lawsuit - Letters, Notices, Flyers, and Press (3 of 4 folders), 1983-1990 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 12-14)
    Original folder reads: "Letters from Congressman Ted Weiss, State Senator Francis Leichter, City Councilwoman Ruth Messinger et al."
  - Lawsuit - Letters, Notices, Flyers, and Press (1 of 4 folders) over-size, 1983-1990 (Box over-size small)
    Map of Tribeca labeled "Appendix A" with three distinct mixed use zoning areas depicted and a note for artists applying for alteration permits.
  - Lower Manhattan Tribeca Reports and Plans (Box -, Folder -)
  - NYC Zoning Plans, Text Changes, and Studies, 1989-2002 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Lower Manhattan Zoning Press, 1986-2006 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
  - Municipal Art Society Report to the Board of Standards and Appeals, 2004 January 8 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)
    Comprehensive Study of Zoning
  - Tweed Courthouse Library Request, 1984-1985 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)